<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The French kinges declaration and confirmation of the Proclamation of Nantes by His M[ajes]tie granted to those of the pretended reformed religion / faythfully translated out of the coppie printed at Paris by Francis du Carroy and Thomas Menard 1613, by J.B.</title>
            <title>Declaration du roy et confirmation des Edits de Nantes. English. 1613</title>
            <author>France. Sovereign (1610-1643 : Louis XIII)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06363</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16831.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101109</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22136598</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22136598</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25135</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06363)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25135)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 965:12 or 1731:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The French kinges declaration and confirmation of the Proclamation of Nantes by His M[ajes]tie granted to those of the pretended reformed religion / faythfully translated out of the coppie printed at Paris by Francis du Carroy and Thomas Menard 1613, by J.B.</title>
                  <title>Declaration du roy et confirmation des Edits de Nantes. English. 1613</title>
                  <author>France. Sovereign (1610-1643 : Louis XIII)</author>
                  <author>Louis XIII, King of France, 1601-1643.</author>
                  <author>Barnes, John, d. 1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 9 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For Iohn Barnes, and are to be sold at his shop neere Holborne Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of Declaration du roy et confirmation des Edits de Nantes.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁸(-A1, A8).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 16831 on reel 965.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France. --  Edit de Nantes.</term>
               <term>Huguenots --  France.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIII, 1610-1643.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25135:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25135:1"/>
            <p>THE FRENCH Kinges Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Proclamation of <hi>Nantes,</hi> by his M<hi rend="sup">tie.</hi> granted to thoſe of the pretended re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion.</p>
            <p>Faythfully tranſlated out of the Coppie printed at <hi>Paris</hi> by <hi>Francis du Carroy</hi> and <hi>Thomas Menard</hi> 1613. By <hi>J. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Imprinted at London for <hi>Iohn Barnes,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop neere Holborne Conduit. 1613.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:25135:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:25135:2"/>
            <head>The Confirmation of the Proclamations of <hi>Nants, graunted by his Maiestie to thoſe</hi> of the pretended reformed Religion.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>EWES,</hi> by the grace of God King of <hi>France</hi> and of <hi>Nauarre:</hi> To all thoſe, &amp;c. Our greateſt deſire ſince our comming to this Crowne, for which we doe continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly implore the grace of God; and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Queene <hi>Regent,</hi> our moſt honorable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ady and Mother, hath continually moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arefully laboured; hath tended to be able
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:25135:3"/>
to mainteine and preſerue all our Subiectes in reſt, peace, and tranquilitie; and in good amitie, vnitie, &amp; concord one with another a matter importing the principall founda<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of the vpholding of this eſtate. To thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> effect, ſo ſoone as it pleaſed God to viſit v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with the ſiniſter accident of the death of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> moſt honored Lord and Father of gloriou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> memorie, wee reſolued our ſelfe to imitat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and walke in the ſame wayes that he had ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken, to attaine to the ſame ende: And hauin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> found, that after he had by his valour reſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red this eſtate into the antient eminenci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thereof, he had with great care, labour, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> foreiudgement; and for a foundation of a aſſured quietneſſe, and perfect reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion among all his Subiectes: and namel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to take from thoſe of the pretended refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion, all occaſion of feare and mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtruſt, which they might conceiue concer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning the libertie and ſafetie of their Perſon Conſciences, Honors, Goods, and Families made, and decreed the ſame which is con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teined in his Proclamation giuen at <hi>Nan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in Aprill. 1598. by the obſeruation where of, and of the ſecret Articles, Briefes, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:25135:3"/>
Rules, made in conſequence thereof, had happely ruled and gouerned his people in peace, euen to his deceaſe. As alſo, one of the firſt actions that we vndertooke in our reigne, tended to diſpatch our Letters of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the xxij. of May 1610. impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a confirmation of the ſayd Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of the ſecret Articles, Rules, and Decrees, giuen to the execution and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the ſame; which at the ſame inſtant we ſent to all our Parliamentes to be verified: and ſoone after, we ſent into all the Prouinces of our Realme, ſome of the principall of our Counſell, and other quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied perſons whom we choſe, as well Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes, as of the pretended reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, to cyment and ſet faſt the entier eſtabliſhment and execution of the ſayd Proclamation, and of the fauours graun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed in ſuite thereof: hauing euer ſince, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued employing whatſoeuer our care and authoritie to this effect.</p>
            <p>But it is come to paſſe, that our good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges haue not wrought that effect, which we might haue deſired, among all our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes; of whom ſome, namely of thoſe of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:25135:4"/>
the ſayd pretended reformed Religion, by ſome ſhadowes which they lightly concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued through certaine diuers accurrences, are entered into ielowſies and miſtruſtes one of another; whereof haue enſued, that they haue ſuffered them ſelues to be caryed, to the augmenting of the ordinarie guardes, ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vp and making prouiſion of Armour, aſſembling of Souldiers, houlding of Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies and Counſels; with other actions, wholly contrarying the tenour and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the ſayd Proclamation: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to neuertheleſſe, wee are content to beleeue; that they haue been induced rather by ſome apprehenſion that they haue taken of them ſelues, and vnder falſe ſhadowes and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, then of any bad mindes or intentes: as hauing alwayes acknowledged thoſe of the ſayd Religion in generall, to haue been very well affected to the good of our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and faſt and aſſured to the regard, fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and obedience, that they owe vnto vs.</p>
            <p>But as this euill may draw after it moſt dangerous conſequeces, wee haue thought it neceſſarie to prouide, and remedie it, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:25135:4"/>
to reeſtabliſh that good loue, intelligence, and ſocietie that ought to be indifferently among all our ſayd Subiectes, to the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of their common quiet; which as it ſeemeth, can not be more aſſuredly brought to paſſe, then by the exact obſeruation of the ſayd Proclamation, ſecret Articles, Briefes, and other Actes, made in ſuite of the ſame; and withall, giuing a new aſſurance to our ſayd Subiectes of the ſayd pretended reformed Religion, of our good inclination in their behalfes, and of that intent that we haue to preſerue, mainteine, protect, and make them inuiolably to enioy all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, grauntes, and graces, that haue been graunted vnto them as well by the ſaid Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, as ſince the ſame, euen as they did in the life time of the late King vntill his deceaſe, as alſo all that haue ſince by vs been graunted vnto them.</p>
            <p>For theſe cauſes and others, thereto vs moouing, hauing put this affaire in delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to our Counſell, wherin were aſsiſtant the Queene Regent, our moſt honoured La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and Mother, the Princes of our blood, and other Princes, with many Officers of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:25135:5"/>
our Crowne, and principall Counſaylours of our Counſell: By the aduice thereof, wee haue ſayd and declared, and doe ſay and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare; will, and it is our pleaſure, that the aforeſayd Proclamation of <hi>Nantes,</hi> togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with our Declaration of the xxii. of May 1610. with all the particular Articles, Rules, Decrees, and other Law diſpatches in conſequence and in interpretation or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of the ſame, ſhall be againe read and publiſhed in all our Courtes and Bayli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wickes of them depending, hauing to the ſame end, and ſo long as need ſhall require, confirmed them; and by theſe preſentes ſigned with our owne hand, doe confirme them.</p>
            <p>WEE will and ordaine, that the whole ſhall be receiued, and inuiolably obſerued, without any contrarying in any ſort or manner whatſoeuer. And in as much as the breaches hereof made by ſome of our ſayd Subiectes, proceeded rather of the ſuſpitious &amp; miſtruſtes where with they were ſlightly caried away, then for want of any affection, will, or obedience; which they alwayes te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified vnto vs in al occaſions that haue been
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:25135:5"/>
offered: as alſo hoping that hereafter, they will conteine them ſelues in their duties vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the obſeruation of our Proclamation and Decrees; Wee will, meane and it is our plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that all Decrees, Actes, and other Expeditions, that haue been giuen and made againſt them, as well in generall as in perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, for any cauſe or occaſion whatſoeuer, ſhall be voyde and as not made, ſo as by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion or in ſute of the ſame, they ſhall not incurre any reproch, danger, or damage; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be hereafter moleſted, or called in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. And herevpon, we doe impoſe ſilence to all our Atturnies general, their ſubſtitutes, and all others: As alſo, wee doe expreſly forbid all our ſayd Subiectes conformably to the ſeuentie ſeuenth, and eighty two Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the ſayd Proclamation, hereafter to make any callinges of Aſſemblies, or hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of any prouinciall Counſels, or other leauies, or gathering of Armes, or men of Warre, or any other actions directly or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly, repugnant to our ſayd Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or Declarations, vnder paine of diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and to be puniſhed as diſturbers of the publicke peace.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:25135:6"/>Wee alſo commaund our welbeloued and truſtie Counſaylours, the people holding our Court of Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> and all other our Courtes of Parliament, and Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Proclamation eſtabliſhed through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this Kingdome, that the aforeſayd Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation of Pacification, ſecret Articles, Briefes, Declarations, and other Letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes to them ſent in conſequence of the ſame; togeather with theſe preſentes, they cauſe immeadiatly to be read and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in all places accuſtomed in ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and the Contentes of the ſame to cauſe to be kept and obſerued, and inuiolab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be maintained; ceaſing, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to ceaſe, all troubles and hinderaunces to the contrary.</p>
            <p>Wee alſo doe enioyne all our Atturnies generall, diligently to ſet to their handes: And in caſe there ſhall hereafter, be any gaineſayers to cauſe ſuch ſeueere procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges againſt them, that the example of their puniſhment may be a reſtraint to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: For ſuch is our pleaſure.</p>
            <p>In witneſſe whereof, wee haue cauſed to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:25135:6"/>
put our Seale to theſe Preſentes.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at <hi>Paris</hi> 
                  <date>the 15. of December the yeare of grace 1612. and of our reigne the third.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Signed <hi>LEWES.</hi>
               </signed>
And vpon the fould;
</closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>By the King being in his Counſell, the Queene Regent his mother preſent.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>DE LOMENIE.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>FINIS.<figure/>
            </trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25135:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
